Tamara Paula Temple





Summary

Working at the intersection of Rails, GraphQL, and React, developing modern web applications with fast response times. Deeply experienced in software architecture, design, and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of web applications, user experience, team building, and processes.

Skills

general business analysis, consulting, facilitat-

ing, software engineering, teaching, web

development

engineering

software APIs, architecture, backend, coding, de-

bugging, frontend, full-stack, GraphQL,

vices, REST, testing, tool chains

libraries + ApolloClient, ApolloServer, GraphQL, jekyll, middleman, Rails, React, Sinatra frameworks

languages CSS3, HTML5, JavaScript, PHP, Perl,

Python 3, Ruby, SCSS/SASS, Shell

tools babel, Emacs and Org-mode, make, Miro, Node.js, Notion, npm/npx, rake, RubyMine, Storybook, thor, webpack,

Webstorm, yeoman (yo)

low-level design, macro- and microser-

PostgreSQL, Redis, TimeScaleDB databases

AWS ECS, EBS, S3, Cloudfront, Netlify, servers

nginx, puma, unicorn

testing Jest, Minitest, RSpec, Testing Library

(CT/CI/CD); Functional Programming; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Program architecture and design; NLP (Neuro-linguistic Programming) practitioner; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Test-/behaviour-driven

Methods Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything – testing, integration, deployment

development; Time series analysis; User-/task-centered design

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA

Additional Training

Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neurolinguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on React, Webpack, GraphQL, JAMstack, Angular, others

Experience

2020-2022 Staff Software Engineer, Drip, LLC, Remote

Primarily focused on providing consumer and market analytics, insights, and guidance in the Drip app that enables Drip customers to become more capable email marketers. Acted as a project manager to plan, document, and track projects for the team. Software architecture and design for major features in the insights area, and providing mentoring, direction and guidance to other engineers in Drip.

- Member of the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion team at Drip, and led the DEI Affinity Groups project to produce a guide for forming and running affinity groups (i.e. employee resource groups) within Drip
- Led a team to produce a mentoring and learning environment at Drip, including a guide for mentors and mentees, tools to find or offer mentoring, connecting mentees with mentors, and reporting results
- Mentored individuals new to the organization and new to software engineering. Provided mentoring, feedback, and guidance to individuals seeking to expand their understanding and skills
- In the absense of any project management or leadership in the insights area, acted to perform discovery, planning, discussion, documentation, and create the Epics and Stories for each project, and monitored seeing it through to completion
- Taught and led several forward-viewing project and team retrospectives to provide learning and actionable changes. Feedback from these was very positive, sometimes the participants were surprised at how well they worked
- Designed an architecture to provide a Guidance System that would be able to take requirements and copy for guidance from any product team and others, and provide it to the front end where needed based on metrices and benchmarks
- Developed a microservice to deliver time scale metrics in order to speed up customer analytics pages
- Developed an architecture for providing recommendations, insights, and proposed next actions to Drip users (i.e. email marketers)
- Contributed on company-wide quality weeks and company-wide SMS feature initiative
- Contributed to engineering-wide improvement projects

2017-2020 API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Minneapolis, Minnesota/Remote

Software engineering across the entire Kickserv application stack from the back end in Ruby on Rails with a Postgresql database, implementing a GraphQL server controller with various queries, types, mutations, and resolvers to implement a GraphQL API, and create a React front end that consumes that GraphQL API with Apolloclient in order to replace the legacy JavaScript code from over a decade of various implementation styles and libraries, giving a modern, cohesive approach to front end web application development.

- o provide queries, mutations, types, and resolvers that call Rails ActiveRecord and ActiveModel models to create, read, update, and destroy records as necessary for the operation of the application.
- architect and develop the JavaScript front end code in React to provide a good separation of concerns ensuring testability and writing tests where none existed prior; lowering maintenance costs, and ensuring easy replaceability to enable new features to be added with less overall effort and more predictability.
- o build Rails models, controllers, views, and React components for new Kickserv features.

- o rewrite several legacy JavaScript and jQuery files into cohesive React component trees.
- implement various POROs (Plain Old Ruby Objects) to extract complicated and repeated code from controllers into testable and repurposeable units, including service objects for interfacing with third party APIs.
- o rebuild all the tooling for building, testing, and delivering front end code with the Rails application, using modern build technology such as webpack (using webpacker), jest, and the JavaScript Testing Library
- document all work in order to provide other current and future engineers information on how to use and extend the GraphQL API and React front end components and architecture
- o mentor, train, coach, and guide other engineers in learning Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, GraphQL, Apollo and the architecture and technologies used in the Kickserv product, as well as useful documentation skills, communication skills, remote team interactions, planning, estimating, and management skills
- 2001-2017 **Web Developer**, *Pontiki Software Crafts*, Mendota Heights, Minnesota/Remote Freelance web design and development, including pro bono work for non-profits and individuals desiring a presence on the Web. Includes finding hosting space, development of information architecture, design layout of site, development and/or repurposing of content, and maintenance.
 - User experience and User-centered design for interactive web sites
 - Database design for dynamic web sites and applications
 - O Creation and developing on frameworks for generating static web sites
 - O Frameworks and infrastructure to implement business logic and web site features
 - O Environments and tools for development, testing, integration and deployment
 - O Teach and coach new developers, running "Toast & Tech" study groups
 - Volunteer mentor/coach/instructor for Women Who Code Twin Cities, Hack-the-Gap, Code Switch (Code for America)
- 2016-2017 **Contract Software Developer**, Software for Good, Minneapolis, Minnesota/Remote Provide software to enable clients to query a large datastore with natural language and return meaningful datasets.
 - o write anisble and shell scripts to deploy project to staging
 - o write training questions and entity extraction code
 - o write extraction, transfer, and load scripts for external data
 - o provide code review and expertise to other project members
 - o wrote mainly in Python
 - o deployments using Ansible to AWS
- 2013-2016 **Contract Software Developer**, *Ackmann-Dickenson*, Minneapolis, Minnesota/Remote Contract development in the areas of Rails and JavaScript on several A-D projects.
 - Pro subscriptions and e-commerce in Brewtoad
 - One-button recipe ordering in Brewtoad
 - Customer Onboarding
 - O Micro-service architecture and implementation
 - O Angular SPA clients for MSA backend
 - Massive and complex data analysis product
 - O Data ETL middle layer to provide a massive speed-up for an e-commerce website

- O Lots of Ruby on Rails and JavaScript
- O Deployments using chef, puppet, and ansible to Rackspace and AWS EBS

1980-present

Various positions, Hewlett-Packard (San Jose, Palo Alto), Shopzilla (Los Angeles), NovuHealth (St. Louis Park), BluewaterBrand (Remote)

Career as a software developer, business analyst, process and technology consultant, author, facilitator, trainer

- Web development in PHP, JavaScript, Ruby on Rails
- O Software development on unix system software
- O Taught relationship-based skills to engineers, managers, and senior execs.
- Consulted with various software development groups within Hewlett-Packard to improve software development capabilities
- O Developed software for network management at Hewlett-Packard
- O Software Quality Engineer manager of 10 engineers
- O Software Quality Engineer